George Daniels MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
George Daniels MD Papers
1921 - 1978
The George Daniels Papers has bulletins, publications, biographical information, and presentations. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.42 linear feet (1 box)
Daniels, George E. (George Eaton), 1896-1987
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1979.0001
Gift of George Daniels, 1979.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
George Eaton Daniels was born on May 17, 1896 in Massachusetts and died in 1987. He received his M.D. degree from Harvard University in 1922. His analysis was in Berlin with Franz Alexander, and he was supervised by Sandor Rado. On his return to the United States, he continued his training at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute. He subsequently became an instructor, a training analyst, and one of its directors. He also served as secretary of the New York Psychoanalytic Society from 1936 to 1939 and as a vice president of the American Psychoanalytic Association from 1939 to 1940.
In 1928, Daniels began to practice psychiatry and psychoanalysis in New York. He also became an instructor and clinical professor of psychiatry at the College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center. From 1945 to 1957, he was on the staff of the Psychoanalytic Center (then the Clinic), where he was a training analyst, teacher, and sought-after supervisor. He was the director of the Psychoanalytic Clinic from 1957 to 1961. Daniels helped found the Association for Psychoanalytic Medicine, originally named the Association for Psychoanalytic and Psychosomatic Medicine. The "Psychosomatic" was soon dropped in the interest of brevity, but its early presence is an indication of how important the area was to Daniels and to some of his early colleagues. He was the Association’s first president.
Throughout his professional career, Daniels remained close to medical practice and medical illness, seeing the latter as a unitary response in which the emotions were an integral part. Together with various colleagues he had nearly forty publications and wrote extensively about the gastro-intestinal tract, particularly ulcerative colitis, and on diabetes mellitus, sex hormones and hormonal replacement therapy, and on the mental aspects of tuberculosis.
Daniels, George E. (George Eaton), 1896-1987; Association for Psychoanalytic Medicine (U.S.); Columbia University. Center for Psychoanalytic Training and Research; Ulcerative colitis
The George Daniels Papers has bulletins and a published history that he wrote detailing his relationship to the Association for Psychoanalytic Medicine and the Columbia Psychoanalytic Clinic is expressed through. In addition to biographical information and reprints of some of his articles, texts of several talks he presented about mental health, ulcerative colitis, and comprehensive medicine are included. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Curriculum vitae and biographical information, 1968 - c. 1978 (Box 1)
  - George Daniels’ manuscript "History of the Association for Psychoanalytic Medicine and the Columbia Psychoanalytic Clinic" and related notes, 1969 - 1975 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Bulletin of the Psychoanalytic Clinic for Training and Research, 1941 - 1953 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Bulletin of the Psychoanalytic Clinic for Training and Research, 1954 - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Texts of addresses "Psychiatry in Medicine," "The Mental Health of the Soldier," and "An Adventure in Comprehensive Medicine", 1921 - c. 1965 (Box 1)
  - Text of talk "Comprehensive Medicine with Particular Reference to Ulcerative Colitis", 1965 (Box 1)
  - Text of commencement address "The Changing Face of Psychiatry", 1967 (Box 1)
  - Text of talk "Ulcerative Colitis", 1969 (Box 1)
  - Reprints by George Daniels about the Association for Psychoanalytic Medicine and the Columbia Psychoanalytic Clinic, 1956 - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Scientific reprints, 1933 - 1943 (Box 1)
  - Scientific reprints, 1944 - 1956 (Box 1)
  - Scientific reprints, 1960 - 1975 (Box 1)